<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>MECH-CAP</title><link>http://moorepants.github.io/eme185-splash/</link><description>UC Davis Mechanical Engineering Capstone</description><atom:link href="http://moorepants.github.io/eme185-splash/feeds/jason-k-moore-phd.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2013 00:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><item><title>Wave Energy Converter</title><link>http://moorepants.github.io/eme185-splash/wave-energy-converter.html</link><description>&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Team: Nick Raymond, Thomas Rumble, Teresa Yeh, Kevin Quach, Alex Beckerman&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Faculty Mentor: Professor Cristina Davis&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Website: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://oceanpowerproject.wordpress.com"&gt;https://oceanpowerproject.wordpress.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ocean holds a vast potential of energy, that if effectively converted,
could be used as a plentiful and reliable source of renewable energy. One way
to capture that energy is through the use of wave energy converters (WEC),
machines that convert the motion of ocean waves into clean electricity. One
possible approach to increasing the use of ocean power in the United States,
and gaining support from the general population, is to give the public access
to a basic design that individuals or collective groups could build and improve
upon. Our goal was to develop the basic framework for a wave energy converter
(WEC) and share this information with the public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://moorepants.github.io/eme185-splash/images/wave-energy-buoy-construction.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To achieve this objective, a team of five mechanical engineering students
designed, built, and tested a fully functioning wave energy converter with the
goal of generating 150 watts of peak power. The WEC was engineered to be
modular, capable of being transported by a light-duty vehicle, and constructed
using off-the-shelf components and parts. To validate the system design, the
team conducted ocean testing in Bodega Bay, California, and measured power
output over the period of five days. Due to premature mechanical failure of the
generator coupling, the device was only able to produce a peak power of 38
watts. Even though the device failed to meet the expected power output, the
team has compiled the following information and shared it on this website in
hopes of encouraging others to take on similar projects and make improvements
to the work that has already been done.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2013 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>tag:moorepants.github.io,2013-10-13:eme185-splash/wave-energy-converter.html</guid></item><item><title>Low-cost Pediatric Treadmill</title><link>http://moorepants.github.io/eme185-splash/low-cost-pediatric-treadmill.html</link><description>&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Student Team: Derek Chow, Adam Li, Norman Lei, Erik Pettitt&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Faculty Mentor: Prof. Cristina Davis&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Easter Seals, an organization dedicated to enriching the lives of those with
autism and other disabilities, tasked us with the design and construction of a
portable treadmill for young children diagnosed with motor disabilities.
Therapeutic use of a treadmill at a young age can accelerate the development of
a child's walking skills. Our pediatric treadmill is designed to fit the
everyday family household. The core concepts of the treadmill's features
closely mirror industrial treadmill design, including the use of a walking
belt, rollers, and an electric motor drivetrain. Intuitive and safe controls
are provided for a supervising adult to operate at speeds in the range of 0.1
to 1.0 miles per hour. Other features of the pediatric treadmill are that it is
lightweight, transportable, and has low initial and maintenance costs.  The
design of the pediatric treadmill aims to provide a viable and long-lasting
solution for promoting development of motor skills in children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://moorepants.github.io/eme185-splash/images/pediatric-treadmill.png" /&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2011 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>tag:moorepants.github.io,2011-10-13:eme185-splash/low-cost-pediatric-treadmill.html</guid></item></channel></rss>