<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>MECH-CAP</title><link>http://moorepants.github.io/eme185-splash/</link><description>UC Davis Mechanical Engineering Capstone</description><lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2016 00:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><item><title>Adaptive Target for Jumping Studies</title><link>http://moorepants.github.io/eme185-splash/adaptive-target-for-jumping-studies.html</link><description>&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Student Team: Jacob Alameda, Cyrus Caretto, Joseph Chua&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Faculty Mentor: Jason K. Moore&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jumping studies in which a person jumps repeatedly for thirty seconds or longer
are conducted assuming the person being tested is giving his or her best effort
with every jump. However, the data collected from such studies shows this is
likely not the case. The team was tasked with designing and building an
adaptive target that adjusted to the performance of the subject. A ceiling
mounted design using a basketball controlled by three pulleys was selected as
the concept to be built. The height of the basketball is controlled by a
stepper motor and Arduino Uno, and responds to two proximity sensors and an
accelerometer which indicates the test subject’s jump heights. This design was
chosen because it was simple to build, easy to store away, and is the best way
satisfy all of our sponsor’s needs and suggestions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2016-10-11:eme185-splash/adaptive-target-for-jumping-studies.html</guid></item><item><title>Automatic Board Feeder for Custom Saw/drill Station</title><link>http://moorepants.github.io/eme185-splash/automatic-board-feeder-for-custom-sawdrill-station.html</link><description>&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Student Team: Micah Starr, Adam Barry, Christopher O'Keefe, Alex Landry&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Faculty Mentor: Jason K. Moore&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Micro-Vu Corporation designs and manufactures optical measurement machines. As
a California based manufacturer, automation is critical to keeping costs low.
To reduce labor intensive processes, Micro-Vu developed a semi-automatic cut
and drill station for 14' wooden boards in the summer of 2015. The primary
purpose of this project is to design, manufacture, assemble, and verify an
automated board-loader and unloader to fully automate the custom cut and drill
station. The solution to this challenge includes pneumatics to simplify the
movement of materials, brushless DC motors to transfer boards from storage
locations to the infeed table, sensors for material location verification, and
PLC programming for the interaction of each component. The final product has
the capability of running unattended for 2 hours and only requires additional
loading of material to continue production.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://moorepants.github.io/eme185-splash/images/automator.jpg" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2016-10-11:eme185-splash/automatic-board-feeder-for-custom-sawdrill-station.html</guid></item><item><title>Bus Jack Caddy</title><link>http://moorepants.github.io/eme185-splash/bus-jack-caddy.html</link><description>&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Student Team: Paul Corcoran, Billy Gong, Tom Phong&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Faculty Mentor: Jason K. Moore&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A caddy was constructed to aid in the installation and removal of a Stertil
Koni JB­160 rolling jack onto a Stertil Koni SkyLift. The purpose of the caddy
is to eliminate the need for an additional recess in the ground that would have
been added to house the permanently mounted jack. The target of the project was
to produce a deliverable that was easy to repair, durable, and economically
feasible. The identified sub­problems that had to be considered were
maneuverability, lifting mechanism, and effectively interface with the lift.
These factors all play an equally important role in the performance and
structural integrity of the caddy because after all, the caddy has to be able
to withstand a heavy load while lifting the jack up to be mounted onto the
SkyLift as well as travel environment of the Unitrans facility. Some
specifications of the caddy are a total minimum weight of 800lbs, a steel
construction, and a base size of about twelve square feet. A fully complete and
working jack was delivered to Unitrans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://moorepants.github.io/eme185-splash/images/caddy-jack-prototype.jpg" /&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2016-10-11:eme185-splash/bus-jack-caddy.html</guid></item><item><title>CNC Cardboard Cuter</title><link>http://moorepants.github.io/eme185-splash/cnc-cardboard-cuter.html</link><description>&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Student Team: Silas Walker, Christopher Loos, Angelo Magliola, Jay Nagin&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Faculty Mentor: Jason K. Moore&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The team &amp;quot;From Here to Woodland&amp;quot; has designed and built a safe CNC machine
capable of cutting cardboard with the ultimate goal of providing students the
opportunity to learn about CNC machines and use the knowledge to make
prototypes of their ideas. The machine is completely open source and made from
easily obtainable parts, making it cheaper than comparable 3D printing methods.
The CNC Cardboard Cutter allows students to cut shapes out of cardboard or make
fold lines in the cardboard from an engraving pass. The cut and fold lines are
used to fit the 2D pieces together and make 3D parts for a variety of
applications which include making templates for painting, sheet metal work or
even art projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://moorepants.github.io/eme185-splash/images/cnc-cardboard-cutter-team.jpg" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2016-10-11:eme185-splash/cnc-cardboard-cuter.html</guid></item><item><title>DIY Powered Wheelchair</title><link>http://moorepants.github.io/eme185-splash/diy-powered-wheelchair.html</link><description>&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Student Team: Simon Quan, Ilia Potanin, Josh Taggard&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Faculty Mentor: Jason K. Moore&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This group was tasked with developing an &amp;quot;open source&amp;quot; power wheelchair which
could be built, maintained, and modified using off-the-shelf components that
helps serve the broader goal to give people with disabilities an option to
build their own chairs without relying on expensive and bureaucratic medical
supply companies. The final design uses readily available parts, is quickly and
easily repairable, and is built using only garage tools. The students
demonstrated a fully working chassis with electronic controls that met the
desired specifications and is thus be able to perform at a level at or above
the current chairs available on the market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe
  width="560"
  height="315"
  src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/7QIGyIN9o2w"
  frameborder="0"
  allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2016-10-11:eme185-splash/diy-powered-wheelchair.html</guid></item><item><title>Improving Sanitation in Cambodia</title><link>http://moorepants.github.io/eme185-splash/improving-sanitation-in-cambodia.html</link><description>&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Student Team: Joanne Wu, Rachel Muradian, and Yao Guan&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Faculty Mentor: Jason K. Moore&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this mechanical engineering senior design capstone project the students
worked on improving sanitation in floating communities along the Tonle Sap lake
in Cambodia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The students partnered with Wetlands Work! (WW!), a social enterprise based in
Cambodia that designs sanitation and wastewater treatment solutions. The
HandyPod is a sanitation solution designed by WW! for use in floating
communities along the Tonle Sap lake. Pilot studies indicate that the HandyPod
system is very effective at reducing pathogenic content in the lake. However,
its $150 price tag is somewhat cost prohibitive. Furthermore, the current
system is built for use with floating houses and is thus not viable for use
with stilted houses and other types of houses along the lake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overall goal of the partnership with WW! was to increase uptake of the
HandyPod system among residents of the floating communities. To achieve this
goal the students focused on two main objectives: (1) minimizing the cost of
the system and (2) adapting the system for use with stilted houses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read more about the project on the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mae.ucdavis.edu/blog/mechanical-engineering-undergraduate-students-work-improve-sanitation-cambodia/"&gt;MAE news&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://moorepants.github.io/eme185-splash/images/floating-toilets.jpg" style="width: 600px;" /&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2016-10-11:eme185-splash/improving-sanitation-in-cambodia.html</guid></item><item><title>Weinbot</title><link>http://moorepants.github.io/eme185-splash/weinbot.html</link><description>&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Student Team: Egan McComb, Ardalan Moazeni, Natalie Pueyo Svoboda, Kyle Turner&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Faculty Advisor: Prof. Cristina Davis, Prof Stephen Robinson&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Sponsor: Professor David Block&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Awards: 2015 Sandia Engineering Design Award&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;More info: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.behance.net/gallery/27587497/Autonomous-Floor-Cleaning-Robot"&gt;https://www.behance.net/gallery/27587497/Autonomous-Floor-Cleaning-Robot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Software Repository: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/egan/weinbot"&gt;https://github.com/egan/weinbot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current crush pad cleanup at most wineries is grossly water inefficient.
This design is an autonomous proof-of-concept industrial winery floor care
robot. The battery powered device can effectively dislodge and collect solid
grape waste from typical winery concrete flooring with minimal water use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/SKNtMgGCCyI"
  frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 11 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2014-10-11:eme185-splash/weinbot.html</guid></item><item><title>Wave Energy Converter</title><link>http://moorepants.github.io/eme185-splash/wave-energy-converter.html</link><description>&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Team: Nick Raymond, Thomas Rumble, Teresa Yeh, Kevin Quach, Alex Beckerman&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Faculty Mentor: Professor Cristina Davis&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Website: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://oceanpowerproject.wordpress.com"&gt;https://oceanpowerproject.wordpress.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ocean holds a vast potential of energy, that if effectively converted,
could be used as a plentiful and reliable source of renewable energy. One way
to capture that energy is through the use of wave energy converters (WEC),
machines that convert the motion of ocean waves into clean electricity. One
possible approach to increasing the use of ocean power in the United States,
and gaining support from the general population, is to give the public access
to a basic design that individuals or collective groups could build and improve
upon. Our goal was to develop the basic framework for a wave energy converter
(WEC) and share this information with the public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://moorepants.github.io/eme185-splash/images/wave-energy-buoy-construction.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To achieve this objective, a team of five mechanical engineering students
designed, built, and tested a fully functioning wave energy converter with the
goal of generating 150 watts of peak power. The WEC was engineered to be
modular, capable of being transported by a light-duty vehicle, and constructed
using off-the-shelf components and parts. To validate the system design, the
team conducted ocean testing in Bodega Bay, California, and measured power
output over the period of five days. Due to premature mechanical failure of the
generator coupling, the device was only able to produce a peak power of 38
watts. Even though the device failed to meet the expected power output, the
team has compiled the following information and shared it on this website in
hopes of encouraging others to take on similar projects and make improvements
to the work that has already been done.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2013 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2013-10-11:eme185-splash/wave-energy-converter.html</guid></item><item><title>Low-cost Pediatric Treadmill</title><link>http://moorepants.github.io/eme185-splash/low-cost-pediatric-treadmill.html</link><description>&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Student Team: Derek Chow, Adam Li, Norman Lei, Erik Pettitt&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Faculty Mentor: Prof. Cristina Davis&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Easter Seals, an organization dedicated to enriching the lives of those with
autism and other disabilities, tasked us with the design and construction of a
portable treadmill for young children diagnosed with motor disabilities.
Therapeutic use of a treadmill at a young age can accelerate the development of
a child's walking skills. Our pediatric treadmill is designed to fit the
everyday family household. The core concepts of the treadmill's features
closely mirror industrial treadmill design, including the use of a walking
belt, rollers, and an electric motor drivetrain. Intuitive and safe controls
are provided for a supervising adult to operate at speeds in the range of 0.1
to 1.0 miles per hour. Other features of the pediatric treadmill are that it is
lightweight, transportable, and has low initial and maintenance costs.  The
design of the pediatric treadmill aims to provide a viable and long-lasting
solution for promoting development of motor skills in children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" src="http://moorepants.github.io/eme185-splash/images/pediatric-treadmill.png" /&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2011 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:moorepants.github.io,2011-10-11:eme185-splash/low-cost-pediatric-treadmill.html</guid></item></channel></rss>