<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>MECH-CAP</title><link>http://moorepants.github.io/eme185a-splash/</link><description>UC Davis Mechanical Engineering Capstone</description><atom:link href="http://moorepants.github.io/eme185a-splash/feeds/jason-k-moore-phd.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate><item><title>Doxie Derby Pulley System</title><link>http://moorepants.github.io/eme185a-splash/doxie-derby-pulley-system.html</link><description>&lt;iframe width="560" height="315"
 src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/pgFlOz-7hQE" frameborder="0"
 allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt;Every year, UC Davis undergraduate engineering students have the opportunity to
display their work at an engineering design showcase in June. This year, a team
of mechanical engineers, by the request of the UC Davis Veterinary Medicine
school, improved the out-of-date pulley system used during the much-adored
Doxie Derby event on Picnic Day.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>tag:moorepants.github.io,2014-10-08:eme185a-splash/doxie-derby-pulley-system.html</guid></item><item><title>Mall-E</title><link>http://moorepants.github.io/eme185a-splash/mall-e.html</link><description>&lt;iframe width="560" height="315"
src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/rloCGs7dZJQ" frameborder="0"
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Team: Jacob Chavez, Andria Farrens, Patrick Reding, Albert Zhu&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Faculty Advisor: Prof. Cristina Davis&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the direction of Prof. Cristina Davis of the Department of Mechanical and
Aerospace Engineering at UC Davis, this team of seniors were tasked with
measuring and plotting the magnetic field within the beam deflector of the
Crocker Nuclear Lab's particle accelerator. The deflector unit is used to
manipulate a beam of particles generated by the cyclotron. The deflector can
focus beams of protons, deuterons, alpha, and helium particles; these different
particles hold different purposes. We chose to complete this task using an
autonomous probing robot. Our group utilized a Parallax ActivityBot with a few
objective-specific modifications. Our design includes a hall sensor, which
allows the robot to measure magnetic fields. The robot is capable of moving the
hall sensor vertically along a screw jack, permitting three dimensional
magnetic field plots. The design also includes a custom mount for an ultrasonic
distance sensor which optimizes the range and precision of the sensor, and
allows the user to track the probe throughout data retrieval. Different areas
of engineering discipline were utilized for this project. The probe was
designed and CADed to facilitate dimension-specific machining. The ActivityBot
chassis was machined to mount the distance sensor and hall sensor. And a
C-based program was constructed from different coding sub-objectives that were
brought together with a Graphical User Interface (GUI) designed for
straightforward user operation in Labview.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>tag:moorepants.github.io,2014-10-08:eme185a-splash/mall-e.html</guid></item><item><title>Strawberry Harvesting Robot</title><link>http://moorepants.github.io/eme185a-splash/strawberry-harvesting-robot.html</link><description>&lt;iframe width="560" height="315"
 src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/JEPbCn02o-4" frameborder="0"
 allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Team members: Colin Brown, Oliver Chen, Vijay Ganesan, Molly Hoelper, Roger LeMesurier, Evan Racah, Scotty Waggoner&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Advisers: Dr. Cristina Davis, Dr. Kent Wilken, Dr. Stavros Vougioukas&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human workers are essential to strawberry harvesting because of their speed,
accuracy, and judgment. However, manual strawberry harvesting requires workers
to carry the strawberries to their collection points, often while traversing on
a narrow and muddy path. Transportation time consumes up to 20% of working time
for strawberry harvesters, and can be a safety issue. The primary objective of
this project is to design, build, and test a harvest-aid robotic vehicle that
will increase the efficiency of human workers by transporting strawberry flats
from the field harvesters to the furrow ends quickly and safely. The robot
should require neither external devices nor modifications to the current field
environment, and operate intuitively in order to minimize training. The robot
will fit in a single 10-inch furrow and be small and light enough to be carried
by two persons (under 50 pounds). The shuttle uses four motors that are mounted
to a lightweight aluminum frame, and includes a tray coupled with a suspension
system to ensure that the strawberries are not damaged by rough terrain. For
navigation, the robot uses hardware including a CMOS camera, several ultrasonic
sensors, and encoders, as well as software including sophisticated image
processing, filtering, and control. This proof-of-concept will allow for future
developments including navigation software and hardware improvements,
suspension refinement, and robot weight and manufacturing modifications.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>tag:moorepants.github.io,2014-10-08:eme185a-splash/strawberry-harvesting-robot.html</guid></item><item><title>Trebuchet</title><link>http://moorepants.github.io/eme185a-splash/trebuchet.html</link><description>&lt;iframe width="560" height="315"
 src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/79ykB5mUBy8" frameborder="0"
 allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Team: Lars Mortenson, Jason Lamb, Donovan Deame, and Kyle Hutchison&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every year, UC Davis undergraduate engineering students have the opportunity to
display their work at an engineering design showcase in June. This year, a team
of mechanical engineers were challenged to build a full-scale, life-sized
medieval catapult called a trebuchet.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2013 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>tag:moorepants.github.io,2013-10-08:eme185a-splash/trebuchet.html</guid></item><item><title>Low-cost Pediatric Treadmill</title><link>http://moorepants.github.io/eme185a-splash/low-cost-pediatric-treadmill.html</link><description>&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Student Team: Derek Chow, Adam Li, Norman Lei, Erik Pettitt&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Faculty Mentor: Prof. Cristina Davis&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Easter Seals, an organization dedicated to enriching the lives of those with
autism and other disabilities, tasked us with the design and construction of a
portable treadmill for young children diagnosed with motor disabilities.
Therapeutic use of a treadmill at a young age can accelerate the development of
a child's walking skills. Our pediatric treadmill is designed to fit the
everyday family household. The core concepts of the treadmill's features
closely mirror industrial treadmill design, including the use of a walking
belt, rollers, and an electric motor drivetrain. Intuitive and safe controls
are provided for a supervising adult to operate at speeds in the range of 0.1
to 1.0 miles per hour. Other features of the pediatric treadmill are that it is
lightweight, transportable, and has low initial and maintenance costs.  The
design of the pediatric treadmill aims to provide a viable and long-lasting
solution for promoting development of motor skills in children.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jason K. Moore, PhD</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2011 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>tag:moorepants.github.io,2011-10-08:eme185a-splash/low-cost-pediatric-treadmill.html</guid></item></channel></rss>